Welcome in. Let's talk about Railway.
There's lots of different ways to host miniature servers out there on the web,
and they can get as big as you need them to be or as
small as you need them to be. They're dynamic in size.
Railway is one of my favorite providers because it's really simple to deploy to.
So, how does a Railway work? Well,
let's first log in so we can see how to get into the system,
and then I'll show you how you can play around and also make sure
that you're, uh, taking care of the monthly invoices and just managing the panel
in general. So, Railway will log in here by clicking Sign In,
and then there's a little hidden element down here where you can choose to
use the email to sign in. I'll go ahead and use it at greenmarkwaste.com,
continue with email, and over on another screen,
I'll go ahead and get that six-digit code. And I'll put it in.
I am enforcing two-factor authentication for all new accounts that I set up for
Greenmark, and I'm always doing them under the IT at greenmarkwaste.com email address.
So that way, anybody, uh, who's in that email address is able to access
it. At present, that's two people. It's me,
uh, Daniel Shanklin, and it's also Michael N.
So, here we go. Two, one eight,
six, nine, three, and that's going to get me inside of the railway system.
There we go. And because I forced it to use two-factor authentication,
I'm going to have to go ahead and set up my Authenticator app right
now. I'll do that, and everyone else can,
uh, share and set up in this when they come in the office.
So that's not a big deal, and we'll also have some recovery codes that
we can do as well. So, I, uh, keep a,
uh, Duo on my phone.
The Duo is what we use at Jetta and also at AIC,
so I like to just add the apps that I use at work
into Duo. So I'm going to click the Add button up here in the
corner, and then I'm going to go to Use QR Code,
and it's going to ask me to take a picture of this QR code
we see on the screen, and it's going to add my account name.
right there, and give me a six-digit code,
and now any time I'm on my iPhone, I can get this code and
type it in. So, we'll click Enable right here, and it looks like it
went away really quickly, those backup codes, so I'll go back and get those
in another time. Alright, so first things first,
let's take a look at how Railway works. Uh,
they organize things in terms of projects,
and you can either do them as a list, or you can do them,
uh, as these cards right here. And then the number of
services inside of a project is something you can easily see if you go
inside of it. And it reads just like a board,
uh, that, where you would,
like, be doing flowcharts or diagrams, and that's because sometimes things link together.
So, Rebro, that is one of the three projects that we're working on right
now. We also have a Greenmark portal, which I may shut down,
because I don't think we need it. Um,
and then there's the QA website as well.
So, these are all three different websites that run as part of the Greenmark
Waste Solutions Project. If I wanted to be able to see what it looks
like in production, I could come over here to settings,
and then scroll down, and I could click on this link right here,
and it would actually open up the tab, and I could see that site.
I'll talk a little bit about deployment here in just a second,
but I'll also show you the same thing over here. If I change to
this, I can now click on Sarebo, and I can see a different login.
This is for the Sarebo website, the other one is for the QA website.
The portal's a third option, and I think this is just something we'll shut
down, or use in a different way.
Okay, one thing to mention. Uhm,
these generally should connect directly to repositories in GitHub,
and you do that so that whenever there's any code changes that a developer
makes, that those changes go directly out to the website.
So you can see the changes live. Sometimes you don't connect them if you
want to make sure that your site is static and it doesn't get accidentally
updated, but 99.9% of the time you're going to want to connect to repo.
So this would be the perfect time to do this. I'm going to click
connect repo, and it's going to say that there are no repos found,
because it's not configured, uh,
that our GitHub account is actually linked through.
Because I, Daniel, set up these,
I can go log in to my,
uh, log in for this, uh, Greenmark Waste,
and I can go fix that, but that's not going to solve the problem
in the long run. So this is a task that I'll have to complete,
and I'll make sure I log how that works.
Just to reiterate, if you want to get code from one system
into another, you have to set up a connector,
and to set up that connector, you need a GitHub account under the same
email. as what you have for Greenmark Waste.
However, that brings me to the next discussion,
which is the project space itself. So if we,
uh, look right here, Greenmark Waste is a company,
and we can go to Railway, and we can go back to Home,
and we can see different projects. The Greenmark Toolkit might be something,
a different project you could work on, but when you click inside of a
project, it's also worth mentioning that we have production sites,
and we have, we could have a demo developer site, we could have a
experimental, like if I was doing A-B testing on a marketing site,
I might want to know, like, which one's driving in more traffic,
you could set up a lot of different copies of a website and give
them different domains and just kind of play around with things,
but for the most part, production is all you need when you're first starting
out on a project. As we progress and get further into this,
we'll end up setting up what we call a develop environment,
it. And then we'll set up a production. This is a classic two-stage rollout,
and that means any code changes that you want to make,
you would first have to make in the develop branch,
test them on that link, go to that URL,
you know, open up a tab to it, take a look, make sure it
passes all the tests, and then you would push it to production.
You intentionally slow down the development,
uh, like, life cycle, you slow it down and stretch it out to make
sure that fewer mistakes are make it to the, to the front end.
Okay, but going back to the administrative panel,
if you're someone who's not a technical, uh,
user of this, but ultimately need to check on the workspace billing,
you can click over here and then choose workspace settings,
and from here we can see these are general settings, I already put the
link in there, uh, preferred deployment region,
it did set that up improperly, so we're going to go ahead and say
that US East is the correct one, and I'll click update region.
Thank you And then next, you could create a Slack channel,
you could book a migration call, there's lots of different ways you could talk
to Railway to get things fixed, which is really cool. I love this idea
of creating a Slack channel to talk to them, because a lot of the
users of Railway are companies that have Slack.
If we go over to people, we'll see that there are currently two members,
one is me from AIC Holdings, and you can be in different domains,
and also IT at Greenmark Waste,
both are admins, and, uh, two-factor authentication is forced right here.
You could also add trusted domains,
so if there's a certain domain that you want to always accept people from,
you could do that. That's a startup thing, I would never use this at
a larger company, because you don't want everybody with a Greenmark Waste email to
be able to get into this thing, right? Um,
plans, we're currently on the Pro plan,
which is at $20 a month, and it gives you a certain minimum amount
of compute. Um,
and, only if you were want- committing a ton of spend would you go
with one of these enterprise plans. So, there's,
uh, Pro plans, there's Hobby plans, for businesses you really want to go with
the Pro plan, it's so inexpensive at $20 a month,
and you'll almost never go over on billing.
So, the way a plan works, it's a $20 monthly subscription,
it's month-to-month, there is no annual contract.
If you use more than $20 worth of credits,
uhm, which typically you won't if you're not a very busy site- a place,
or a very busy site. If you don't use more than $20 worth of
credits, then your minimum spend of $20 is what they charge you for the
credit card. Otherwise, they are going to tack on extra fees,
because it's variable cost billing, that's extremely common.
You can also go look at the usage and see what the current costs
are. As you can see, these projects have been up You for a certain
amount of time, and the current estimated monthly cost for this entire three-stage
project is $4.79.
Really, really inexpensive. That can go up a lot as people start to use
the site more, calculate things more, et cetera,
and we can get that at some other time as well. Over here on
the billing side, I currently use my personal credit card so that I can
get through the first stage of the video game. And then I'm going to
go ahead and and time. I'm going after I send an email to Greenmark,
I'm going to invite the accounting group from there, in which case they'll be
an admin in the account and then they can go change the credit card
billing, and if I've already just paid $20,
I'll ask for a small reimbursement, no biggie on that one.
Um, a lot of this other stuff is just things that we can learn
over time, but I wanted to make sure I gave a full rundown of
what Railway is and kind of how it fits into the picture.
The way to think about it is, anytime you write code for something,
anything, and you have that code written,
you eventually need someone to host that code in the cloud so that it
can actually do tasks, and so Railway is a way to take your code
that you've written from your computer, put it on GitHub,
and then suck it into Railway and they automatically create a computer that hosts
your site, your worker, your data copier,
your email, your AI bot, whatever it is that you've built,
they're the host of that, and then they just charge you for the privilege.
This is like classic, um, the most classic thing that's happening right now in
cloud computing is exactly this. These containerized services,
and the most, uh, common one that we know of is So,
you could move from Railway to AWS.
You could also move to Google Cloud Provider,
GCP. You can move to Microsoft Azure.
These are all kind of, sort of interchangeable because they all host the code.
Railway just happens to be my favorite. And,
as you can see, they raised $100 million in the Series B.
They're a pretty big deal now because they're starting to blow up all due
to AI. Really simple and effective. If you have any questions,
let me know. Thanks for watching.